Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 47: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), Miracles of Jesus (Tä'ammərä Iyassus), late 18th century; 2 cols., 17 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two miniatures. No case. Wooden boards covered in stamped leather, stitched and leather-covered spi
  - Miracles of Mary Interspersed With Miracles of Jesus, late 18th century; Located on folio 3r-110r. (Unitid 47)
    - Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 85r-86v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary helped a monk to escape the monastery of Qäləmon when persecuted by other monks (Budge, Mary, 28).
    - Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 86v-88v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of the cannibal of Qəmər (Budge, Mary, 29).
    - Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 88v-89v. (Unitid 47)
    - Tenth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 89v-91v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Jewish leader begged Pilate to burn the body of Jesus (Strelcyn 16).
    - Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 91v-92v. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 92v-93r. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 93r-94r. (Unitid 47)
    - Eleventh Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 94r-96r. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus rose from the dead (Strelcyn 16, 37).
    - Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 96r-97v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Archangel Gabriel took the body of the Virgin Mary.
    - Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 97v-99r. (Unitid 47)
      the Virgin Mary appeared in the monastery of Däbərä Mətəmaq.
    - Synaxarium Entry for the Sixteenth Day of Yäkatit, on the Assumption of the Virgin Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 99r-102v. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 102v-103v. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 103v-106v. (Unitid 47)
    - Twelfth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 106v-107v. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus recovered the fish stolen from a fisherman (Strelcyn 16, 9).
    - Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; 1 item Located on folio 107v-110r. (Unitid 47)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 48: Missal (Mäśəhäfä Qədasse), 1889; 2 cols. 24 lines [fols. 5r-41r], 19 lines [fols. 42r-124r]. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. With musical notation. Two miniatures. No case. Wooden boards; broken upper board, repaired with string. Leather-covered spine. Fol. 1rv: Part of spine binding. The number "2165" appears upside down in Arabic numerals. Fols. 2v, 3v-4r, 124v-125v, 41v: Blank. (Unitid 48)
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Outline of decorative häräg
  Illustrations: Fols. 5r, 8r, 10v, 17r, 20r, 34v, 35r, 45r, 49r, 59r, 69r, 78r, 85r, 90r, 91v, 101r, 108r, 112r, 116r, 118v: Decorative härägs.
  Illustration: Fol. 4v: Outline in black ink of angel with drawn sword. With decorative border
  Illustration: Fol. 84v: Outline of priest with hand cross (not original to the text).
  Fol. 3r: A note made in 1896 EC listing the witnesses who can confirm the paternity of a daughter (in another hand).
  Fols. 9v, 16v, 36v: In the supplications for the king, the king mentioned is King Mənilək [r. 1889-1913].
  Fols. 20v, 45r, 49r, 59r, 78r, 91v, 114v, 116r: Some owners' names mentioned: Kəfəlä Maryam and his father Gäbrä Maryam.
  Fols. 24r: Another owner's name is mentioned: Kəfəlä Səyon.
  Fols. 24v, 25v, 33v, 35r, 39r: Metropolitan bishops' names mentioned: Abba Sälama [r. 1841-1867] and Abba Pətəros [r. 1876-1889].
  Fols. 49v: Metropolitan bishop's name mentioned: Abba Matewos [r. 1889-1926].
  Date of text (1889 AD) is estimated based on several items in the text, including mention of the bishops' names and the king's name. Abba Sälama [r. 1841-1867] died in 1867. Abba Pətəros [r. 1876-1889] was replaced by Abba Matewos [r. 1889-1926] in 1889, who was in Ethiopia since 1881. The text includes a prayer for the recently deceased Abba Sälama on fol. 25v, so it cannot have been made before 1867. It probably was not made after 1889 because the text mentions the current metropolitan, Abba Pətəros. The text also mentions King Mənilək [r. 1889-1913] who only overlaps with the current metropolitan, Abba Pətəros, for one year, 1889 AD. The latest date actually mentioned in the manuscript, in another hand, is 1896 EC [1904 AD].
  Owners: Kəfəlä Maryam, Gäbrä Maryam, Kəfəlä Səyon.
  References: Marcos Daoud and H. E. Blatta Marsie Hazen, The Liturgy of the Ethiopian Church (Cairo, Egyptian Book Press, 1959); Ernest Hammerschmidt, Studies in Ethiopic Anaphoras, 2nd rev. ed., (Stuttgart 1987). Catalogs: EMIP 27, 46, 59, 72; Streclyn ?
  - Office Prayer, 1889; Located on folio 5r-17r. (Unitid 48)
    - Prayer of the Covenant, Sälotä Kidan, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 5r-8r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplications, Mästäbqä', 1889; 1 item Located on folio 8r-11v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Sick, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 8rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Traveler, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 8v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for Rainfall, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 8v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for Farming (Lit. "Fruits of the Earth"), 1889; 1 item Located on folio 8v-9r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for Rivers, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 9rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the King, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 9v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Departed, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 9v-10r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Catechumens, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 10r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Peace of the Church, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 10rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany, Liton, for the Days of the Week, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 10v-14v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Miracle of Mary, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 10v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Mary, Lä-Nəgətä Kulənä, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 10v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Monday, Enzä Nä'äkwäto, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 11rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Tuesday, Səməkä Həyaw, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 11v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Wednesday, Lätərus Egzi'o, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 11v-12r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Thursday, Kämä Tadhənänä, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 12rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Friday, Täzäkkär Egzi'o, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 12v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Saturday, Sobä 'äkko Egzi'abəher, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 12v-13r. (Unitid 48)
      Fol. 12v: There is an error, the scribe replaced the litany for Saturday with the litany for Holy Saturday.
    - Litany for Wednesday, Lätərus Egzi'o, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 11v-12r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Sunday, Lä-'amälakä Məhərätt, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 13r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Dead (Lit. the Sleeping), 1889; 1 item Located on folio 13rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Dead, Egəzi'ä Həyawan, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 13v-14r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Dead, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 14r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Vespers, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 14rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Prayer of Supplication, Nägś, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 14v-17r. (Unitid 48)
  - Ordinary of the Mass and Anaphoras, 1889; Located on folio 17r-122v. (Unitid 48)
    - Ordinary of the Mass, Sərə`ata Qədasse, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 17r-34v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of the Apostles, Qədasse Häwarəyat, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 35r-44v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Our Lord, Qədasse Egəzi', 1889; 1 item Located on folio 45r-49r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Mary Attributed to Cyriacus of Bəhənsa, Qədasse Maryam Gwäsə'a, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 49r-58v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of John, Son of Thunder, Qədasse Yohannəs Wäldä Nägwädgwad, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 59r-69r. (Unitid 48)
      Fol. 59r: The scribe made a mistake, titling the Anaphora of John Son of Thunder, the Anaphora of John Chrysostom
    - Anaphora of the 318 Orthodox Fathers, Qädase Zä-Śäläsətu Mə'ət, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 69r-78r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Epiphanius, Qədasse Epifanəyos Abiy, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 78r-84v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Gregory, Brother of Basil, Qədasse Gorgorəyos'əhəwä Basələyos, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 85r-89v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Dioscorus, Qədasse Diyosəqoros Emqədəmä 'aläm, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 90r-91v:. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Athanasius, Qədasse Atənatewos Asämə' Läkəmu, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 91v-101r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Basil, Qədasse Basələyos, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 101r-108r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of John Chrysostom, Qədasse Yohannəs Afä Wärəq Nahu Nəzenu, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 108r-112r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Jacob of Serugh, Qədasse Zä-śərug, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 112r-116r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Gregory [the Wonder Worker], Qədasse Gorgorəyos, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 116r-118v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Cyril, Qədasse Qerəlos, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 118v-122v. (Unitid 48)
      Fol. 118r: The scribe made a mistake, titling the Anaphora of John Chrysostom as the Anaphora of Cyril.
    - Hymns Which Are Parts of Each of the Preceding Anaphoras, Śärawitä, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 123rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Seal of the Bread of the Host, With Indications of Which Portion Goes to the Priest and Deacons, 1889; 1 item Located on folio 124r. (Unitid 48)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 49: Psalter. Dawit, 1922; 1 col. [3r-147v], 22 lines; 2 cols [148r-166r], 22 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Six miniatures. Leather case. Plain wooden boards, stitched and open spine. (Unitid 49)
  Illustration: Fol. 1v: Miniature of a mustached man in purple and red. Probably the owner.
  Fols. 119v: Missing lines inserted in upper margin.
  Owner: Ejəgu Nəguśe.
  Scribe: Aläqa Ayəna'aläm.
  - Psalms, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 3r-128r. (Unitid 49)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 128v-141r. (Unitid 49)
  - Song of Songs (With Musical Notations), 1922; 1 item Located on folio 141r-147v. (Unitid 49)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1922; Located on folio 149r-161r. (Unitid 49)
    - Monday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 149r-150r. (Unitid 49)
    - Tuesday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 150r-152r. (Unitid 49)
    - Wednesday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 152r-154r. (Unitid 49)
    - Thursday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 154r-156v. (Unitid 49)
    - Friday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 156v-158r. (Unitid 49)
    - Saturday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 158r-159v. (Unitid 49)
    - Sunday, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 159v-161r. (Unitid 49)
  - Gate of Light, 1922; 1 item Located on folio 161r-166r. (Unitid 49)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 50: Unidentified, early 18th century; 1 item Two wooden boards covered in red stamped leather with detailed tooling. No manuscript or binding 33.5 x 33.8 cm (Unitid 50)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 51: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 1 col., 22 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Three miniatures. It seems the leather cover of the text was added later. The leather case is too small for the text, it fits the width and depth, but not the length. Leather cover, four stitches, parts of spine enforced with leather and black yarn. Fols. 1r, 13r, 25r, 37r, 49r: Quires are marked with Ethiopic numerals: quire 1, 2, etc. Fols. 1r, 23r, 31r, 39r, 50r: Red yarn sewn through the corner of the relevant folios marks the daily readings (Unitid 51)
  An incomplete Psalter.
  Illustration: Fol. 3v: Miniature of Saint Gabriel with the three holy children (painted over the text).
  Illustrations: Fols. 11v, 23r, 31v: Decorative Härägs.
  Illustration: Fol. 36v: Miniature of crowned King David raising hand and with winged angel (painted over the text).
  Illustration: Fol. 59v: Talismanic drawing of grid with nine squares and faces in center square and outer corners (painted over the text).
  - Psalms, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 1r-60v. (Unitid 51)
    Incomplete, Starts At the End of Psalm 59 and Ends in the Middle of Psalm 118. Fols. 54v-60v: Psalm 118 includes additions about the spiritual meanings of the Hebrew Alphabet.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 52: Images (Mälkə'a Guba'e), early 19th century; 1 col., 14 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Six miniatures. No case. Glossy wooden boards, lower board missing. Open and stitched spine. Fols. 1r-2v, 34v, 39v-40v, 57rv, 60r, 61v: Blank (probably included for illustrations). (Unitid 52)
  Illustration: Fol. 33r: Black ink drawing of angel with drawn sword.
  Illustration: Fol. 34r: Crude pencil drawing of face.
  Illustration: Fol. 38r: Crude black ink drawing of Crucifixion scene, with the Virgin Mary and John the Evangelist. Caption: "Savior of the world crucified at Qäranəyo [Golgotha, the place of the skull], Mary, John."
  Illustration: Fol. 39r: Crude pencil drawing of the crucifixion.
  Illustration: Fol. 60v: Miniature of Saint George and the Dragon with Berutawit (original to the text, in red and gold, blue may have been added later).
  Illustration: Fol. 61r: Miniature of the Virgin Mary and the Christ Child with angels with swords (original to the text, in red and gold, blue may have been added later).
  Fols. 20v-24v: Blank with pencil scrawls.
  Fols. 19v, 50v, 62v: Previous owner's name erased "Wäldä Marəyam" and scribbled over with red ink. Below the erasure is the name "Täklä Amanu'el" in red ink.
  Fols. 37v-38r: A note of ownership in later hand with pencil: "This book belongs to Yəlma Dänkäle."
  Fol. 38v: In later hand, in pencil, a warning against stealing the book or erasing in it.
  Fol. 61r: "Gäbrä Egzi'abəher" written beneath the miniature (the original scribe's name).
  Fol. 64r: Crude pen trial.
  Fol. 64v: A note of ownership in later hand in ink, two names are given: "Aläqa Astärayä of Tämben. Kidanä Marəyam."
  References: See references listed in manuscript no 7, 11.
  - Image of George, Zä-Säleda Mogäs, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 3r-20r. (Unitid 52)
  - Image of Gabriel, Mälkə'a Gabri'el, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 25r-33r. (Unitid 52)
  - Image of the Savior of the World, Mälkə'a Mädhane Aläm, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 35r-50v. (Unitid 52)
    (Chaîne, "Répertoire," No. 164)
  - Image of George, Tämahəsänəku, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 51r-62v. (Unitid 52)
  - A Magical Prayer Against Enemies, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 51r-62v. (Unitid 52)
    In later crude hand with blue ink.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 53: The Five Pillars of Mystery (Aməsətu A'əmadä Məśətir), 1800s; 2 cols., 17 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Five miniatures. Leather case, missing strap. Glossy wooden boards; stitched and open spine. Fols. 83rv and 90rv: Detached. Fol. 90r: Blank (Unitid 53)
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Miniature of the Virgin Mary and Christ Child (with angels on the left and right).
  Illustration: Fol. 24v: Miniature of Saint George slaying the Dragon.
  Illustration: Fol. 50v: Miniature of the Virgin Mary: Coronation, by the Trinity.
  Illustration: Fol. 66v: Miniature of the Virgin Mary and Joseph?
  Illustration: Fol. 82v: Miniature of the monastic leader with his disciple.
  All miniatures are painted over the existing text and do not relate to the text. They seem to have been painted by the twentieth-century "speckled garment artist" described in Steve Delamarter and Melaku Terefe, Ethiopian Scribal Practice 1: Plates for the Catalogue of the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project. Portland, OR: Wipf and Stock Publishers, 2009.
  The Five Pillars of Mystery is in Amharic, but with many quotes from the patristic literature in Ge'ez.
  Fol. 90v: A note in Amharic in another, later hand that starts: "My Father Gebre Hiwot Sadequ, please prepare a parchment for me. I also will do whatever you ask."
  Fol. 1r: The decorative border has been highlighted with a ballpoint pen.
  Fols. 9r, 17r, 25r, 33r, 41r, 51r, 59r, 67r, 75r, 83r: Quires are marked with Ethiopic numerals: quire 1, 2, etc.
  References: Published works on The Five Pillars of Mystery includes a translation into Amharic by Addis Ababa: Tasfa Press, 1952 EC. The Five Pillars of Mystery have also been cataloged in EMIP 51; EMML 1648, 1815; Strelcyn 50.1 See Encylopedia Aethiopica, vol. 1, p. 248.
  - Introduction, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 1r-5r. (Unitid 53)
  - The Mystery of the Trinity, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 5r-21v. (Unitid 53)
  - The Mystery of the Incarnation, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 21v-47r. (Unitid 53)
  - The Mystery of Baptism, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 47r-64v. (Unitid 53)
  - The Mystery of the Eucharist, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 64v-77v. (Unitid 53)
  - The Mystery of the Resurrection of the Dead, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 77v-89v. (Unitid 53)
  - A Magical Prayer for Long Life, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 90v. (Unitid 53)
    In another, later hand.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 54: Synaxarium (Lives of the Saints) Sənksar, circa 1770-1830; 3 cols., 38 lines, 155 leaves on vellum. Written in black ink, with rubrics and titles in red. 39 miniatures in color. No case. Contemporary blind-tooled leather over wooden boards. Some staining (mostly finger staining, here and there small waterstains). Original binding shaken, covering to joints and edges with large defective spots. Covered and stitched spine. Spine cover is newer. Fol. 155v: blank. (Unitid 54)
  Illustrations: 39 miniatures. Fol. 1v: Four miniatures, each of equestrian saints with ornate border. Upper left one holding a spear; upper right, one slaying a bull; lower left, one holding a spear; and lower right, one holding a spear. Further miniatures on fol.s 2r (4), 2v (4), 26v (2), 43v (1), 60r (4), 60v(4), 67r (4), 91v (3), 120r (4), 120v (4), and 155r (1).
  This Synaxarium (Senkessar) contains the collection of the lives of saints from the history of the Ethiopian Christian church and the lives of Ethiopian saints with the lectures to be read at their anniversaries, similar to a martyrology of the Roman church. This codex covers the second half of the year, from Mäggabit to Pagwemen (August to December). Every vita is followed by Salam stanzas (Ethiopian poetry). The beautiful miniatures in vibrant colors are executed in the so-called first and second Gondar style and are based on well-known representations from different stylistic periods. The first images of saints on horseback cite a 17th-century folded parchment leave from the Gondar region (cf. Heldman et al., African Zion: The Sacred Art of Ethiopia, 1996 no.103), the 8 miniatures at the beginning of the 8th quire are based on a codex for the Passion Week from the latter half of the 15th century (ibidem, no. 89). The same goes for the 8 miniatures at the end of the quire (Annunciation, Crucifixion, the Ethiopian Saint Gäbrä Mäfäs Qeddus) and the 8 images at the end of the 14th quire with miracles of the Virgin Mary (ibidem, no. 90). The image of Mary covering almost a whole page at the end of the codex and the portraits of the apostels cite similar representations in known older manuscripts (ibidem, no.11). The small ornamental drawings in black and red ink used as paragraph separators are a characteristic style called "Art of Säwa," developed in the Säwa region at the end of the 18th/beginning of the 19th century. This supports the estimated date of the codex: the text was probably written at the end of the 18th or beginning of the 19th century in the Gondär region and the miniatures were added at the same time.
  Ornamental drawings in red and black ink are present in a few places to indicate paragraph breaks. They are in the style of the "Art of Säwa," which emerged in Säwar Province at the end of the 18th/beginning of the 19th century (cf. Chojnacki, Major Themes in Ethiopian Painting. Äthiopische Forschungen 10 (Wiesbaden 1983), pp. 469-524. (Description provided by Veronica Six, Hamburg.)
  The codex was commissioned by Häbtä Kiros for himself and his wife Sergutä Sellase, the scribe's name is given as Henbaba Dengel.
  Owner: Məhərka Giorgis, Sərgutä Səllasse, Häbtä Kiros.
  Scribe: Hənbabe Dəngəl.
  Purchase, Harteveld Livres Anciens.
  Restricted. Consult staff for access.
  - Sənksar (Synaxarium for the Second Half of the Year), circa 1770-1830; Located on folio 3r-155r. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Mäggabit, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 3r-26r. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Miyazya, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 27r-43v. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Gənbot, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 44r-66v. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Säne, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 68r-91v. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Hamle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 92r-126v. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Nähase, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 126v-150r. (Unitid 54)
    - Entries for Pagwume, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 150r-155r. (Unitid 54)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 55: Scriptural Commentary, 1700s; 1 item 61/4 x 4 inches (Unitid 55)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 56: A Book of Magical Prayers With Talismanic Drawings, early 19th century; Manuscript on vellum, 35 leaves, mostly in gatherings of 8, many of the leaves are stained and rubbed, and the text is at times difficult to read. 2 columns, 16-20 lines in different hands [variously 2-4 mm in height], written in black with the usual rubrics, together with some sections entirely in red, ruling and pricking visible in part, there are numerous talismanic drawings in black and red ink throughout the text, as well as three figure drawings in black with some slight red-brown and grey colouring [ff.33v, 34r, 35r]; bound between plain wooden boards, the rear board split and repaired. Fols. 34v, 35v: Blank. (Unitid 56)
  Illustration: Fol. 3v: A drawing in purple ink of Jesus and another figure in a reed boat addressing a now feint figure outside a house ( ?). The text above the drawing, also in purple ink, is now only partly legible and seems to mention an individual called Berhanä Mäsqäl.
  Illustrations: Fol. 4r: A collection of talismanic drawings.
  Illustrations: Fols. 5v-6v: [mostly in red] A collection of talismanic drawings, followed by a prayer for the "drowning" of demons.
  Illustrations: Fols. 7rv: Two grid charts, the second of which is titled "My Lord Jesus Christ, with this chart save me from mäqurañña [possibly meaning here 'demonic possession'].
  Illustrations: Fols. 8r-9r: [in red] Further grid charts followed by a prayer for binding demons, barya, zar, etc., with talismanic drawings and figures.
  Illustration: Fols. 32v: Three grid charts entitled "for Monday", "for Wednesday," and "for Thursday," respectively.
  Illustration: Fol. 33r: A crude drawing of a bird and talismanic letters [harägwi fidäl, lit. "knotted letters"].
  Illustration: Fols. 33v-34r: A drawing of a supplicant with accompanying servant being led by the Virgin Mary towards the figure of Christ in majesty [f.34r]. The supplicant may be a priest as evidenced by his turban and the prayer stick carried by his servant. The text reads "how — (name erased) made supplication through Our Lady Mary and with his [sic] beloved Saviour of the World."